A Guide to the Nathaniel Francis Cabell Papers, 1722-1879
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Nathaniel Francis Cabell Papers, 1722-1879
Library of Virginia
2
.625 cu. ft.
Nathaniel Francis Cabell
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of J. Staunton Moore, 22 May 1912.
Alternative Form
Also available on microfilm (Misc. Reel 287).
Biographical Information
Nathaniel Francis Cabell was born 23 July 1807 at "Warminster" in Nelson County, Virginia, to Nicholas Cabell, Jr. (1780-1809) and Margaret Read Venable Cabell (1782-1857). He graduated from Hampden Sidney College in 1825 and from Harvard in 1827. Cabell settled in Prince Edward County, Virginia, in 1827, then moved back to Nelson County in 1832, settling at the family home, "Liberty Hall." Cabell wrote and published articles on religion, education, and agriculture. He married first Anne Blaws Cocke (1811-1862), daughter of General John H. Cocke (1780-1866), 14 September 1831, and they had six children. He married second Mary M. Keller of Baltimore, Maryland. Cabell spent the last few years of his life living with one of his sons in Bedford County, Virginia, where he died 1 September 1891. Cabell was buried in the family cemetery at "Liberty Hall" in Nelson County.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1722-1879, collected by Nathaniel Francis Cabell (1807-1891) of County, Virginia, to be used in a work on the history of Virginia agriculture. Papers consist of bibliographies, constitutions, correspondence, diaries, essays, indexes, memorandums, minutes, patents, recipes, reports, resolutions, testimonials, and transcripts; and concern agriculture in Virginia from the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. Topics include agriculture, mainly tobacco, wheat, corn, and peas; livestock, mainly cattle, horses, sheep, and swine; farm implements like threshers, circular saws, mill equipment, and other tools; and manures for fertilizers. Some papers relate to the Agricultural Society of Albemarle and to the Virginia Agricultural Society. One letter comments on the possible sale of Mount Vernon in the 1850s.
Correspondents include James Barbour, Joseph C. Cabell, Nathaniel Francis Cabell, Dr. William Cabell, John H. Cocke, James M. Garnett, Thomas Jefferson, James Madison, William Massie, Peter Minor, Thomas Mann Randolph, Thomas Jefferson Randolph, Richard Sampson, John S. Skinner, Edmund Taylor, and Yardley Taylor.
Some letters contain notes by Cabell containing further information on topics and/or information on the writers.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- A List of Manuscripts Relating to the History of Agriculture in Virginia, collected by N. F. Cabell, and now in the Virginia State Library,January 1913, published in the Virginia State Library Bulletin, volume 6, number 1., 11 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Book spine and title page. Manuscript Letters, & C, from 1722 to 1879, and title gives provenance of collection., 1 leaf and 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Extracts, [1722], from Lowthorpe's Abridgment of The (English) Philosophical Transactions, Illustrative of Virginia Husbandry in Colonial Times. Extracts from the Journal of John Clayton., 12 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Extracts, 1724, from Hugh Jones' Present State of Virginia concerning agriculture in Virginia., 13 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Extracts, 1749, from the diary of the Reverend Robert Rose on the managment of tobacco., 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letter, 6 June 1771, John Howard, Botetourt [County, Virginia], to Dr. William Cabell, Amherst [County, Virginia], concerning severe flooding along the James River., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Letter, 5 February 1778, Landon Carter to Richard Henry Lee at Chantilly, regarding the process of making sugar, molassas, and liqour from corn stalks., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Letter, 19 March 1782, Paul Carrington to William Cabell, Jr., Amherst [County], informing Cabell he is sending him some cattle., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Letter, 22 May 1802, Archibald D. Alexander, Montpellier, Georgia, to Major Edmond Read, Charlotte County, [Virginia], on agricultural conditions in Georgia., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Letter, 9 December 1803, Dr. J. M. Galt to John H. Cocke, Mount Pleasant, on the cultivation of Scotch Broom., 1 leaf. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Letter, 6 September 1804, Josiah Scholefield, Lancaster, [England], to Joseph C. Cabell, London, [England], concerning circular saws., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Letter, 24 June 1805, John Taylor, Hazelwood, [Caroline County, Virginia], to Dr. George Washington Tennent, [Port Royal, Virginia], regarding the cultivation of the Yetman pea., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Letter, 7 August 1807, Francis Watkins, Sr., Amherst [County], to Nicholas Cabell, Jr., concerning a crop of wheat on Elk Island., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Letter, 2 February 1808, John Brown, Goochland [County, Virginia], to Nicholas Cabell, [Albemarle County, Virginia], concerning the value of burnt grass., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Letter, 22 September 1808, Philip Tabb, Toddsbury, [Gloucester County, Virginia], to John H. Cocke, New Canton Post Office, [Buckingham County, Virginia], detailing the growing of corn on Gloucester County lowlands., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Letter, 21 May 1812, Wilson Cary Nicholas, Warren, [Albemarle County], to John H. Cocke, Fluvanna [County, Virginia], offering to purchase sheep from Cocke., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Letter, 12 July 1813, Randolph Harrison, Bremo, [Fluvanna County], to John H. Cocke informing Cocke of the state of his farm and crops., 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Copy of patent, 1814, of J. Hall's specification concerning a new improvement in cultivating corn., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Letter, 29 May 1815, L. Wells, New York, to General [John H.] Cocke, [Fluvanna County], concerning the management of sheep., 2 p., part of letter missing. (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Letter, 15 July 1815, Peter Minor, Ridgeway, Albemarle County, to General [John H.] Cocke, [Fluvanna County], concerning an experiment for testing the efficacy of Hall's patent method of raising corn., 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Letter, 13 August 1815, Bushrod Washington, Mount Vernon, [Fairfax County, Virginia], to St. George Tucker, [Williamsburg, Virginia], regarding the construction of pise' [prize?] buildings., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Constitution and rules, n.d., of the Agricultural Society of Albemarle., 5 p. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Extract, n.d, from proceedings of the Agricultural Society of Albemarle, including questionaire to planters and farmers., 2 p., printed. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Copy, n.d., of Joseph C. Cabell, [Nelson County, Virginia], answers to questionaire of the Agricultural Society of Albemarle., 1 leaf. (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Note, n.d., on objects for the attention and inquiry of an agricultural society by Thomas Jefferson., 2 leaves. (Box 2, Folder 17)
- List, 1817, of subjects for essays assigned to members of Albemarle Agricultural Society by Peter Minor., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Letter, 22 March 1817, Thomas Jefferson, [Monticello], to General [John H.] Cocke, [Fluvanna County], sending him plants., 2 p., copy. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Letter, October 1817, John H. Cocke, [Fluvanna County], to Peter Minor, [Albemarle County], concerning the Hessian fly., 2 leaves. (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Extract, 1 October 1817, of letter from Joseph C. Cabell, [Nelson County], to General [John H.] Cocke concerning the Agricultural Society of Albemarle and agricultural societies in England., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Letter, 14 October 1817, Thomas Mann Randolph, Monticello, [Albemarle County], to James Madison, [Montpellier, Orange County, Virginia], informing Madison of his election as president of the Agricultural Society., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Letter, 14 October 1817, Thomas Mann Randolph, [Albemarle County], to Peter Minor, [Albemarle County], calling for an extraordinary meeting of the society., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Letter, 25 October 1817, Thomas Mann Randolph, [Albemarle County], to Joseph C. Cabell, [Nelson County], containing suggestions as to the proper course of the society., 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Report, 12 May 1818 [read], of Dr. Frank Carr on practices of agriculture., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Letter, 1818, John H. Cocke, [Fluvanna County], to Peter Minor, [Albemarle County], concerning manuring for wheat., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Essay, n.d., on management of sheep in Scotland., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Letter, 4 September 1818, John Overton, Louisa [County, Virginia], to an unknown recipient concerning the growing of corn., 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Letter, 26 September 1818, Peter Minor, Ridgeway, [Albemarle County], to Mr. [James] Madison, [Orange County], on draining of land., 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Letter, 7 November 1818, John Marshall, Wilson Cary Nicholas, John Coalter, John Wickham, and John Adams, for the Virginia Agricultural Socity to the Secretary of the Agricultural Society of Albemarle regarding the receipt of a communication., 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Letter, 10 October 1819, James Barbour, Barboursville, [Orange County], to Peter Minor, [Albemarle], concerning the application of society funds toward greater production., 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Report, n.d., of committee on James Barbour's suggestions concerning the application of funds to premiums., 6 p. (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Letter, 12 January 1820, John Adams to John H. Cocke, [Fluvanna County], informing Cocke that he has been elected president of the Society for Promoting Agriculture in Virginia., 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Letter, 9 February 1820, H. Holmes, Winchester, [Virginia], to Peter Minor, [Albemarle County], concerning stone fences., 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Letter, 8 April 1820, James and Jacob Douglas, Alexandria, [Virginia], to Peter Minor, [Albemarle County], forwarding seeds., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Report, 8 May 1820 (read), of Peter Minor on gathering clover seed., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Letter, June 1820, David Porter, Washington, to Philip Barraud, [Norfolk, Virginia], concerning ruta baga., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Letter, 20 July 1820, Thomas Mann Randolph to Joseph C. Cabell regarding horizontal plowing., 2 p, copy. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Letter, 15 August 1820, Dabney Minor, Orange [County], to Peter Minor, [Albemarle County], regarding farm diaries., 8 p. (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Letter, 5 October 1820, Ben Coleman, [Spotsylvania County, Virginia], to Peter Minor, [Albemarle County], concerning shoeing oxen., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Letter, 21 October 1820, John S. Skinner, Baltimore, [Maryland], to Joseph C. Cabell, [Nelson County], regarding farm accounts and improvements., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Letter, 14 February 1821, Andrew Cocke, New York, to Thomas Jefferson concerning seed drills., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Letter, 25 February 1821, Jesse Buel, Albany, [New York], to John S. Skinner, [Baltimore] regarding corn., 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Letter, 25 February 1821, Thomas Mann Randolph, Richmond, [Virginia], to Peter Minor, [Albemarle County] on purchasing horses from Spain., 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Letter, 24 July 1821, John Stuart Skinner, Baltimore, to Joseph C. Cabell, [Nelson County], concerning Brown on Rural Affairs, and Skinner's own work on agriculture., 7 p. (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Letter, 12 October 1821, Peter Minor, Ridgeway, [Albemarle County], to Joseph C. Cabell, [Nelson County], regarding tobacco., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Letter, 17 October 1821, Peter Minor, Ridgeway, [Albemarle County], to Joseph C. Cabell, [Nelson County], regarding 2 acres of corn., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Letter, 29 March 1822, John Skinner, Baltimore, to Joseph C. Cabell, [Nelson County], regarding [Peter] Minor's Appendix to Essay on Tobacco., 1 leaf. (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Letter, 22 April 1822, Thomas Mann Randolph, Richmond, to John H. Cocke, [Fluvanna County] on Cocke's horse, Roebuck and his stock, and Cocke's threshing machine., 1 leaf. (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Letter, 1822, Thomas Jefferson Randolph, [Albemarle County], to Peter Minor, [Albemarle County], concerning green manures., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Circular letter, 21 October 1822, by James Madison containing resolutions for a professorship of agriculture at the University of Virginia., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Letter, 17 November 1822, James M. Garnett for the Agricultural Society of Fredericksburg to the Agricultural Society of Fredericksburg regarding a professorship of agriculture at the University of Virginia., 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Letter, 15 December 1822, Peter Minor, [Albemarle County], to John H. Cocke, [Fluvanna County] concerning a professorship of agriculture at the University of Virginia and his plow business., 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Letter, 8 December 1824, John Stuart Skinner, Baltimore, to Joseph C. Cabell, [Nelson County], concerning copies of the memoirs of the Pennsylvania Agricultural Society., 1 leaf. (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Letter, 16 July 1825, Robert Stanard, Richmond, to an unknown recipient regarding wheat., 1 leaf. (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Letter, 21 July 1825, John Wickham, [Richmond], to John H. Cocke, [Fluvanna County], concerning wheat seed., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Letter, 1 September 1825, Thomas Melville, Pittsfield, [Massachusetts], to John S. Skinner, [Baltimore], regarding corn crushers., 1 leaf. (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Letter, 12 September 1825, John S. Skinner, Baltimore, to Joseph C. Cabell, [Nelson County] regarding Cabell's letter on corn crushers., 1 leaf. (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Letter, 24 October 1825, James Barbour, Washington, to Peter Minor, [Albemarle County], on a professorship of agriculture at the University of Virginia and on how internal improvements could help agriculture., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Essay, 3 March 1827, by Jesse Edgington about sheep., 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Letter, 1 February 1830, John Winn to Elisha Boyd regarding a drum machine. Includes Boyd's reply. Winn represented Fluvanna County and Boyd represented Berkeley County in the House of Delegates at teh time the letters were written., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Extract, n.d., from Eubank on Indian Antiquities., 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Copy, n.d., of essay on Jethro Tull., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Letter, 1 July 1832, Rueben B. Patteson to Nathaniel Francis Cabell,[Nelson County], containing a proposed rotation scheme of crops for five fields written by Cabell's father Nicholas Cabell, Jr., in 1808., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Letter, 1 December 1832, Richard I. Gaines, Wardfork, Charlotte [County], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], concerning using leaves as manure., 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Letter, 18 June 1833, John H. Craven, Penpark, [Albemarle County], to John H. Cocke, [Fluvanna County], concerning buckwheat., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Letter, 2 February 1837, Reverend J. Kilpatrick to John H. Cocke, [Fluvanna County], concerning the Bedford breed of swine., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Letter, 9 February 1837, James M. Garnett, [Essex County, Virginia], to John H. Cocke, [Fluvanna County], regarding Maryland twin corn., 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Letter, 3 August 1837, William W. Gilmer, [Charles City County?, Virginia], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County] on raising hogs., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Letter, 12 April 1842, John Morris, Warren, [Albemarle County], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], concerning the cultivation of corn and an essay by R. B. Patteson., 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Letter, 18 October 1843, Hill Carter, Shirley, [Charles City County], to John H. Cocke, [Fluvanna County], regarding the management of Shirley., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Letter, 5 October 1846, Richard Sampson to John H. Cocke, [Fluvanna County], concerning the use of lime and internal improvements along the James River., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Letter, 23 November 1846, Thomas Jefferson Randolph, Edgehill, [Albemarle County], to Joseph C. Cabell, [Nelson County], concerning stall-feeding cattle., 2 leaves. (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Letter, 26 December 1846, Thomas Jefferson Randolph, Edgehill, [Albemarle County], to Joseph C. Cabell, [Nelson County], regarding stall-feeding cattle., 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Letter, 25 February 1847, Dr. Joseph E. Muse, Cambridge, Maryland, to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], on Spanish tobacco., 3 p. (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Letter, 9 April 1847, Richard Sampson, Richmond, to John H. Cocke, [Fluvanna County], concerning Irish potatoes., 1 leaf. (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Letter, 1 February 1850, Alexander Rives to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], about a corn cob crusher., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Letter, 9 September 1853, P. V. H. Steenbergen, Poplar Grove, [Mason County, (West) Virginia], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], containing reminiscences on Virginia agriculture., 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Letter, 17 December 1853, John Janney, Leesburg, [Virginia], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], regarding gypsum and clover seed., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Letter, 30 December 1853, Reverend Peyton Harrison to William B. Harrison, [Prince George County, Virginia], concerning plantatin management., 9 p. (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Letter, 2 January 1854, Daniel Janney, Loudoun [County, Virginia], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], describing agriculture in Loudoun County., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Letter, 5 January 1854, F. S. Sampson to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], on farming., 1 leaf. (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Letter, 9 January 1854, Ben A. Donald, Bedford County, [Virginia], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], on sun-cured tobacco., 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Letter, 11 January 1854, Yardley Taylor, Purcellville, [Virginia], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], on the development of agriculture in Loudoun County., 6 p. (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Letter, 13 January 1854, Nathaniel Francis Cabell, Warminster, [Nelson County], to Dr. Arthur Lee Brent, concerning George Washington's contributions to agriculture., 6 p. (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Letter, 8 February 1854, William Massie, Pharsalia, [Nelson County], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], on graduated furrows., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Letter, 15 February 1854, Reverend Peyton Harrison to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], concerning farm management., 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Letter, 17 February 1854, John Augustine Washington, Mount Vernon, [Fairfax County], to Dr. Arthur Lee Brent concerning George Washington's agricultural diary and the possible sale of Mount Vernon., 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Letter, 4 March 1854, H. M. Smith, Richmond, to William B. Harrison, [Prince George County], regarding corn shellers., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Letter, 13 March 1854, William B. Harrison, Brandon, [Prince George County], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], regarding corn shellers., 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Letter, 12 May 1854, Philip St. George Cocke to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], concerning green sand as manure., 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Letter, 24 July 1854, Franklin Minor to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], stating that he has gone through his father's papers for autographs of his father and of James Madison, and for papers on the Agricultural Society of Albemarle., 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Letter, 25 August 1854, W. T. Walker, Dover, [Loudoun County?], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], containing reminiscences of Richard Sampson and of agriculture in Albemarle County., 8 p. (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Letter, 14 September 1854, Stapleton C. Snead, Bellevue, Nelson [County], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], regarding threshing machines., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 58)
- Letter, 18 September 1854, William Massie, Pharsalia, Nelson [County], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], concerning stone fences., 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Letter, 30 September 1854, Thomas S. Pleasants, Petersburg, [Virginia], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], concerning a revolutionary-era plow in Petersburg., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Letter, 30 September 1854, William L. Booker to Frank G. Ruffin regarding the books and papers of William Meriweather., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Note, [30 September] 1854, from Dr. Joseph B. Anderson containing additional information on William Meriweather., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Extracts, [copied 30 September 1854], from 1802 agricultural diary of William Meriweather., 2 p. (Box 2, Folder 59)
- Letter, 11 October 1854, Yardley Taylor, Loudoun County, to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], regarding the collection of minerals., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Letter, 13 October 1854, H. E. Watkins to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], concerning a crop of wheat on Elk Island almost fifty years earlier., 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Letter, 16 October 1854, William Massie, Pharsalia, Nelson [County], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], concerning rock fences., 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Letter, 27 October 1854, R. McPheeters, Augusta County, to the president of the Virginia Agricultural Society., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Letter, 28 October 1854, William B. Harrison, Brandon, [Prince George County], to Edmund Ruffin, with enclosure, letter, 9 October 1854, from John R. Todd to William B. Harrison on the Smithfield bacon trade., 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 60)
- Letter, 14 November 1854, Thomas S. Pleasants, Petersburg, to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], concerning the Cassia chamaecrista., 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Letters, 26 February, 15 March, 16 May 1855, Reverend Jesse S. Armistead, Cumberland [County, Virginia], to Joseph C. Cabell, [Nelson County], regarding the manuring of tobacco., 11 p. (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Letter, 4 April 1855, W. T. Walker, Dover, [Loudoun County?], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], on Richard Sampson's method of farming., 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Letter, 23 April 1855, Edmund Ruffin, Prince George [County], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], regarding American Husbandry., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Letter, 12 May 1855, Thomas S. Pleasants, Petersburg, to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], concerning Dr. Greenway's papers on agriculture., 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Letter, 21 January 1856, T. F. Nelson to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], concerning Nelson's invention of a guano attachment to a wheat drill and the theft of the idea from him., 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Letter, 16 September 1853, John H. Beale, Mason County[(West) Virginia], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County] regarding artificial woods., 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Letter, 16 May 1859, A. H. H. Bernard, Mansfield, [Nelson County], to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], concerning the cultivation of corn., 4 p. (Box 2, Folder 61)
- Letter, 16 July 1859, Henry S. Randall, Cortland Village, New York, to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], regarding sheep husbandry., 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Report, 3 November 1859, of the Committee on Testimonials, Virginia Agricultural Society., 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Report, 1860, of the Committee on Essays., 3 p., copy. (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Letter, 4 September 1860, J. A. Gibson to Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], concerning curing tobacco., 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Letter, 14 November 1860, Nathaniel Francis Cabell, [Nelson County], to Edmund Taylor, [Campbell County, Virginia], concerning Taylor's essay written under the pseudonym Agricola, and submitted to the State Agricultural Society. Includes copy of letter, 3 October 1860 from Charles B. Williams, Richmond, submitting the essay from Agricola; copy of Agricola's letter to Williams asking him to submit it to State Agricultural Society; and copy of Agricola's letter to the society., 17 p. (Box 1, Folder 64)